<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A word in season: or, A discourse of the three estates to wit, the truly civil, truly spiritual, and false ecclesiastical estate: shewing, that this last, or third estate, is a remainder of popery, and ought to be taken away. Presented to the King and Queen's most excellent Majesty, together with the right honourable the Lords and Commons assembled at Westminster.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67045</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3547A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220041</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831479</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831479</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35942</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67045)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35942)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2122:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A word in season: or, A discourse of the three estates to wit, the truly civil, truly spiritual, and false ecclesiastical estate: shewing, that this last, or third estate, is a remainder of popery, and ought to be taken away. Presented to the King and Queen's most excellent Majesty, together with the right honourable the Lords and Commons assembled at Westminster.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35942:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A WORD in SEASON:</hi> OR, A DISCOURSE OF THE Three Eſtates: TO WIT, The Truly Civil, Truly Spiritual, AND FALSE <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Eſtate:</hi> SHEWING, That this Laſt, or Third Eſtate, is a Remainder of Popery, and ought to be taken away.</p>
            <p>Preſented to the <hi>King and Queen's most Excellent Majeſty,</hi> Together with the Right Honourable the LORDS and COMMONS Aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:35942:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35942:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>King and Queens Moſt Excellent Majeſty:</hi> Together With The Right Honourable THE <hi>Lords and Commons</hi> Now Aſſembled at WESTMINSTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it Pleaſe Your Moſt Excellent Majeſties, and You Right Honourable Patriots,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Civil State being the Power and Sword of the Lord, to do his Commandments: Therefore when GOD commanded King <hi>Saul</hi> utterly to Deſtroy <hi>Amalek,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> did it not fully, but ſpared <hi>Agag</hi> their King, and the beſt of the Cattle to Sacrifice to the Lord: The evil effect that befel <hi>Saul</hi> for doing the Lords Command negligently; was firſt to himſelf; God Rent the Kingdom from him; and then to the whole houſe of <hi>Iſrael, Haman</hi> one of the ſeed of <hi>Agag</hi> the <hi>Amalekite,</hi> ſought the Deſtruction of all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> had not the Lord by a miraculous Providence prevented it.</p>
            <p>Now, Why muſt <hi>Amalek</hi> be utterly deſtroyed? Becauſe when God had Delivered his People out of Old <hi>Egypt,</hi> and they were Travelling Peaceably, Faint and Weary, through the Wilderneſs, to the Promiſed Reſt, the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> a Type of Heaven; <hi>Amalek</hi> destroyed ſome of them: Even ſo the very reaſon is, why the Lord hath ſaid, The Kings
<pb facs="tcp:35942:3"/>of the Earth ſhall hate the Whore, eat her Fleſh, and burn her with Fire, even theſe Spiritual Amalekites, the deſtroyers of the Lords People, that are come out of the Spiritual Egypt, Travelling to the Heaven of Everlaſting Happineſs and Reſt with Christ in Glory, through the Wilderneſs of this World.</p>
            <p>Now then, becauſe when this Work was begun by former Kings in this Nation, as after is ſhewed, and not yet fully done (in utterly destroying theſe Spiritual Amalekites, not in their Perſons, but out of Church and State, ſo that they might bear no Office of Truſt there,) but have Retained them ſtill; ſee what had like to have been the effects thereof; their Elder Brethren were coming in a pace to poſſeſs their old Places, and had ſo far prevailed with the King (to his great ruine) to deſtroy the Nation out of their Rights and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and perhaps out of their Lives at length, if the Lord had not by his miraculous Providence wrought our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance; ſo that the Lord hath once more put into the hands of You the Supream Powers of this Nation, to do the work the Lord hath commanded, fully: Pardon my boldneſs, There is a time to ſpeak, if fitly ſpoken, how good it is; which may ſerve but as a Candle to your Sun-light, in the due ſence of theſe things; therefore this may only ſerve to ſtir up your minds by way of Remembrance, That if this work be fully done by You, a Bleſſing will be upon all your good works, in ſetling this Nation in Peace; as ſaith the Scriptures, <hi>When the Lord giveth Quietneſs, who can make Trouble? And when he hideth his Face, who can behold him? whether it be done againſt a Nation or a Man only,</hi> Job. <hi>34.29.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35942:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A WORD in SEASON:</hi> OR A DISCOURSE OF THE <hi>Three Eſtates.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Lord God Creator of the Heavens and the Earth and Sea, with all the plenty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, hath made of one Blood all Mankind to dwell one the face of the Earth, and hath diſpoſed unto them the bounds of their Habitations; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Wiſdom hath appointed but two State-Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars or Legs for the Nations to ſtand upon, the one Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, the other Spiritual; the Civil State is God's Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Magiſtratical Government under divers Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, as the Lord diſpoſeth, and the Civil State ſee beſt, as Princes, Senators, Judges, Kings, for all Powers are of God, whatſoever be their Titles, Dignities or Forms of Government: In reſpect whereof, they are called humane Creations or Ordinances, and are to be ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto for the Lord's ſake, for as much as there is given them an Excellent Majeſty, being next under God, Head of the Commonwealth, the Lords Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants on Earth, and for their perfect Rule and Guide
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35942:4"/>in Government is given them the ſecond Table of the Royal Law of God, as a moſt ſure Foundation to ſquare all their Laws by to govern their people, who are not to judge for Man, but for the Lord, ſo ſhall they not bear the Sword in vain, but uſe it to the Glory of God, in puniſhing Evil-doers (without reſpect of Perſons) and for the praiſe of them that do well, of which Truſt or Stewardſhip committed unto them, they muſt ſhortly give an account to the great Judge, the Lord Jeſus, at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>The other State or Pillar, is the Spiritual Rule or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Lord Jeſus now in the Kingdom of his Mediatorſhip in his Church on Earth, <hi>whoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is not of this World, neither are the Weapons thereof Carnal, but Spiritual, and mighty through God, to the pulling down of strong holds, caſting down Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and every high thing that Exalteth it ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Knowledge of God, bringing into Captivity every thought to the Obedience of Christ;</hi> ſo differeth it from the Civil State: Unto this Spiritual Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is given the firſt Table of the Royal Law; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereunto, are all the Laws given by Chriſt to his Subjects in his Kingdom, his Church; in all things they are to do, or keep in the Worſhip and Service of God his Father, written in his laſt Will and Teſtament, ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his precious Blood, unto which nothing may be added to, or taken from by any mortal upon pain of all the Curſes written in the Book of God.</p>
            <p>Theſe being the two only States ordain'd of God on Earth, for all mankind to be ſubject unto in the Lord, and the nature of them being ſo different the one from the other, as the nature of a thing Civil and Spiritual, ſo that they may not be mixt together in their Offices nor Adminiſtrations; therefore the Lord conſtituted the Civil State in the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> and the Spiritual State
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35942:4"/>in the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> ſo that it is and ever was a Sin of High Nature, for the Civil States Office to do the Work which properly belongeth to the Spiritual States Office; but when King <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> preſum'd to break Gods Order, in doing the Work which belong'd to the Spiritual States Office to do, the Lord ſmote him with Leproſie to the Day of his Death, and Dethron'd him from his Kingly Office, and ſeparated him from Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with his Church or People.</p>
            <p>Therefore, the Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> (who only without Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, can bear that Title of Arch-Biſhop, or Chief Biſhop of our Souls; who is the only Lord Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, and Overſeer of his Churches, walking in the midſt of his Golden Candleſticks) would not meddle with the Work which properly belong'd to the Civil States Office, to give Judgment on a Woman taken in Adultery, no nor divide Temporal Inheritances between Brethren; ſo that when there aroſe Strife among his Apoſtles, which of them ſhould be accounted the Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt; Chriſt the Lord reproved them, and ſaid unto them, <hi>the Kings of the</hi> Gentiles <hi>exerciſe Lordſhip o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, and they that exerciſe Authority upon them, are called Benefactors, but ye ſhall not be ſo;</hi> That is, to take on you the Title of Politick Princes, neither to be Lords Spiritual in nor over Churches: Thus we may clearly ſee, why the Lord divided his Law into Two Tables, becauſe the One appertaineth to the Spiritual State in thoſe things which belong to the Kingdom of Chriſt in his Worſhip and Government, and the Other is as a perfect Rule to all Civil States Government, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all thereby, that the Civil and Spiritual States, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their Offices nor Adminiſtration, may be join'd together in One Perſon; ſo that the Offices being ſo different, they may not meddle with the Work in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that belongeth to the Other, becauſe it is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35942:5"/>forbidden, not only by Gods Word, but alſo it is againſt the very light of Nature, as the Philoſopher ſaith: It cannot ſtand with the Actions of theſe Two Offices, namely the Civil and Spiritual; ſo different the One from the Other, that one Man ſhould perform both Works together, but muſt needs fall out; when both Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are to be done, the one would be omitted; ſo either God is not duely Serv'd, or the Civil State muſt ſuffer Damage.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that theſe are the Two States ordain'd of God, and that they may not be mixt together without the breach of Gods Order; How cometh it to paſs, that there is a Third State in the Nations never Ordain'd of God, nor found to be approv'd of God by his Word, which is a State partly Civil, and partly Spiritual; under the Tides of Arch Biſhop, Lord-Biſhop, who fit in the Civil States Privy Councils, and in their great Council of Parliaments, and alſo they ſit as Lords Spiritual, in and over many Churches or Congregations? Now from whence took this State its Original or Beginning, who ſit as Law-Makers in the Civil States Councils, and alſo do ſit as Law-Makers in Worſhip to God in their Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Aſſemblies? ſurely this is a Monſter of a State, partly Civil and partly Spiritual, yet neither really Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil nor Spiritual, but a counterfeit compound of both, firſt brought forth in its infancy among the old Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh <hi>Egyptians,</hi> who would have their Prieſt Princes, and the Scripture is witneſs to it, as it is written Prieſt of <hi>On,</hi> Prince of <hi>On, Gen.</hi> 41.45. ſo when the Church of God at <hi>Rome</hi> fell into deep Apoſtacy from <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſoon after ſhe was deliver'd from the cruel rage of the Heathen Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperor being converted to the Faith, under whom great comfort and peace was injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Church of God, ſo that then the Biſhops were Biſhops of particular Congregations as their name ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35942:5"/>ſo was their charge, an Overſeer to ſo many as could meet in one place, and communicate together in partaking of the Ordinances of the Goſpel; but in a ſhort time, about the middle of the fourth Century, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of particular Congregations, were not contented to be an Overſeer to One, no nor to Two nor Three Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but <hi>Diotrephes</hi>-like, ſtrove to have the Preeminence over all the Congregations, which at laſt was obtained by <hi>Sylveſter</hi> the firſt, Pope; and hereupon ſaith <hi>John, There aroſe another Beaſt out of the Earth, having two horns like a Lamb;</hi> So as Horns ſignifyeth Power, ſo this beaſtly third State, the Pope, the head of the Clergy, of his own making, was proclaim'd, as Writers ſay, for a Vice God, the Invincible Monarch of the Common-Wealth, and vehement Conſerver of the Popiſh Omni-potency: So that although by his two Horns like a Lamb (he pretended Power from Chriſt) he began to ſpeak like a Dragon againſt the ſealed number of Gods Elect, which departed from the iniquity of his invention in Worſhip and Miniſtry, and ſo refuſed to receive this Beaſts mark in their right hand or forehead, that is pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately or publickly to ſubmit to his decrees in Worſhip; ſo that the Beaſts decree was ſo hot againſt the Godly, as by the like High Commiſſion Court in <hi>England</hi> of the ſame Authority, ſome time paſt, that no man might buy or ſell, ſave he that had the mark of this beaſtly Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, or the name of the Beaſt, or the number of his name; now what is the Beaſts name or marke, but his Law, Decrees and Orders he commanded to be obey'd in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, for ſo the name of <hi>Christ</hi> is his Law &amp; Power, that all his People are commanded by their Obedience, to ſet their ſeal, <hi>that Chriſt is the True God, and the only Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver in Worſhip:</hi> ſo that hereupon we read, that the Dragon was wroth with the Woman, and went to make War with the remnant of her Seed, which keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35942:6"/>of God (in worſhip) and have the Teſtimony of <hi>Jeſus;</hi> yea, ſo enraged was one of the Limbs of this beaſtly Clergy, as he raileth againſt the Laws and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſt in his Teſtament, which Chriſt hath commanded to be obſerved in the Worſhip of God to the Worlds end; namely, <hi>T. C.</hi> the then eſteemed Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> in his anſwer to <hi>Martin Marprelate,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the Orders and Ordinances Christ hath in his Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment left to his Church, were but temporary, while the Church was under heathen Tyrants; and where the Goſpel is embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by a Chriſtian Prince, they are not only not neceſſary, but inconvenient, yea intolerable, as bringing in the ſubverſion of the Land, raiſing up tumults and uproars, and withdrawing the People from obedience to their Magiſtrates;</hi> by this we ſee how this beaſtly Clergy inveigheth againſt Chriſts holy Orders and Ordinances in Worſhip; and do not the ſame Clergy in this our day, by their actions ſpeak the ſame words; ſo long as the Service-Book, taken out of the Popes Maſs-Book, is obeyed, and the Holy Orders and Commands the Primitive Chriſtians obey'd in the Worſhip of God, is not ſuffered to be practis'd in Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches according to Chriſts Teſtament; ſo that as the Civil State hath their Books, Statutes and Records, (<hi>Eſther</hi> 6.1.) Charters, together with the Second. Table of the Moral Law, to inſtate themſelves in their Civil Rights and Privelidges, under their Supream Head and Governour: The true Eccleſiaſtical State have Laws and Statutes contain'd in the Old and New Teſtament, to be obſerved under the Government of <hi>Chriſt</hi> their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Head, in theſe the Charter of the Rights and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of the Citizens in the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> are found.</p>
            <p>The falſe Ecleſiaſtical State under their head the Pope, <hi>Apollion,</hi> that Deſtroyer, together with their Arch and Lord Biſhops, they have Books of Cannons and Articles,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35942:6"/>Book of Ordination, Book of Homiles, and Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayers; ſo that the Citrizens under this State, are ſtrictly commanded to keep and obſerve them; ſo that as one of their Clergy complain'd in their ſecond Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to the Parliament in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time, no Preacher may without danger of the Laws utter all the Truths compriz'd in the Book of God; it is ſo circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd within the compaſs of ſuch Statutes, Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Articles, Cannons; the Book of Common-Prayer, the Biſhops Cannons, every Biſhops Articles in his Dioceſs may not be broken or offended againſt, but with more danger than to offend againſt the Bible.</p>
            <p>Now, ſhall we ever live to ſee the day when there ſhall be obeyed but one <hi>Law-giver</hi> in Worſhip, and the Word of God, the only Judge to teach who is this only <hi>Law-giver,</hi> namely, <hi>the Lord Jeſus,</hi> as it is written, <hi>The Lord is our Law-giver</hi> (or Statute-maker) <hi>in Worſhip;</hi> and again, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>There is one Law-giver who is able to ſave, and to destroy;</hi> to wit, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who hath all Power in Heaven and in Earth given unto him, therefore he commandeth his Servants, the Apoſtles, <hi>to Teach all Nations;</hi> only what he hath commanded to be obey'd in Worſhip; and hereupon ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, He that is a Prophet, or Spiritual, let him acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the things I have written to you;</hi> namely, to the Churches, are the Commandments of the Lord; <hi>and he that will pot hear that Prophet Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy'd from among his People:</hi> And again, ſaith the Lord Jeſus, <hi>Bring theſe mine Enemies that would not that I ſhould reign over them, and ſlay them before me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore be Wiſe, O ye whom the Lord hath put in Authority, kiſs the Son leaſt he be angry; give no longer your Power to the Beaſt aforeſaid, and no longer let the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Service and devis'd Worſhip, be confirm'd by Law in Worſhip; but let the commands
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35942:7"/>of the Lord Jeſus be Exalted only, remembring God's Promiſe, that you may do his Work, as he hath ſaid; <hi>The Horns or Powers that did ſupport the Whore, ſhall hate her, and ſhall make h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Deſolate and Naked; Eat her Fleſh, and burn her with Fire:</hi> This Work was well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan by King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. and King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th. when they aboliſh'd out of their Dominions, the Popes Supremacy, the Lord <hi>Abbots, Cardinals, Monks</hi> and <hi>Friers;</hi> and dried up a great part of the River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> which brought in the Gain to theſe ſpiritual <hi>Babylonians,</hi> and convened their Revenues to civil Uſes, and gave much thereof to charitable Uſes; and becauſe theſe Kings did not the work of the Lord throughly, as God hath commanded to be done, and was done on <hi>Old Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> a figure of the <hi>Spiritual Babylon;</hi> as it is written, <hi>The Lord would cut off from</hi> Babylon <hi>the name and remnant, Son and Nephew, and ſweep it with the beſom of Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and this is not fully done yet on the <hi>Spiritual Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> as it muſt be done, ſo long as the Office of <hi>Arch</hi> and <hi>Lord Biſhops, Arch-Deacons, Parſons, Vicars, Curates,</hi> and many other of that Brood, remain in Office in Church and State, which Chriſts Teſtament maketh no mention of: And that this muſt be done, is ſhewed by a Mighty Angel, who took a ſtone, like a great Mill-Stone, and caſt it into the Sea; ſaying, <hi>Thus with violence ſhall this great City</hi> Babylon <hi>be thrown down, and ſhall be found no more, becauſe in her was found the Blood of the Prophets and of Saints, and of all that were ſlain upon the Earth:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, this City <hi>Babylon, Myſtery-Babylon, the Mother of Harlots and Abomination of the Earth,</hi> which Reigneth over the Kings of the Earth; is not contain'd within the natural walls of <hi>Rome</hi>'s City, but this City reacheth ſo far, as her Rules and Orders and Commands in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is obey'd, in what Nation ſoever; ſo then <hi>Babylon</hi> the <hi>City,</hi> will not be deſtroy'd out of <hi>England,</hi> ſo long
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35942:7"/>as by Law, her Miniſtry which is deriv'd from the Pope and his ſervice in VVorſhip, is Obey'd, Practic'd, or Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, therefore hath the Lord by his wonderful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence put an opportunity in the hand of the Supream Authority of this Nation, to Aboliſh all that hath but the ſcent of Romiſh Invention in Worſhip; when as by the example of the Godly Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> You are call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon by the Lord to do as they did, to wit, <hi>Jehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat, Ezekiah,</hi> but more eſpecially, that young King <hi>Joſiah;</hi> who ſo ſoon as he heard of the Judgments of God denounced againſt his Land and People, called for the Book of the Law to be read before him, and by it comparing the acts of his Fore-fathers, and preſent ſtate of his Kingdom, Rent his <hi>Cloaths;</hi> and for fear of the Judgments of God, in the Sixteenth year of his Age, and Eighth year of his Reign, begun to ſeek the Lord, and in the Twelf year begun to purge out of his Dominions the Reliques of Idolatry, to wit, all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices or Inventions of Men ſet up by former Kings in the VVorſhip of God, and Aboliſhed the falſe Miniſtry call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Chemarims<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſo called, either for the black Garments they wore, or for being ſmok'd in offering Incenſe to the Idols (See the Margent in the Bible in Folio in 1 <hi>King</hi> 22.5. and <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.4.) Now the like muſt be done in removing the remaining part of the Popiſh Miniſtry out of Office, either in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> in the Nations, together with all the devis'd Service in Worſhip; ſo ſhall the Kings or <hi>Civil State,</hi> dry up the remaining part of the River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and take the Lordly Prelatical Revenues into their hand, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to Civil Uſe; and likewiſe to make void that Law which confirmeth the decree of Pope <hi>Paſcales,</hi> that Tythes ſhould be given to the Prieſt, that ſo Tythe (that Jewiſh Heav-Offering under the Law) may no more
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35942:8"/>be impos'd upon the Conſcience of the People of God in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which Law hath undone many thouſand Families, that in Conſcience to God could not pay Tythes, becauſe the paying of Tythes, is to deny Chriſt to become in the Fleſh, who was the end of the Ceremonial Law, the paying of Tythes being a part thereof; no man that Truly feareth God, ought to pay it, ſo that the Tythes may return to every Owner, unjuſtly exacted from them whoſe they are, as well that as the reſt of their Eſtate, out of which the Tythes was exacted, by Pope <hi>Paſcales</hi> decree; ſo that as the Goſpel is Free, Gods gift to poor Sinners, apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt by Faith therein to be their Redeemer, Prophet and King, may by a free and willing Covenant joyn themſelves to the Lord, to walk in his ways, and as God ſhall beſtow his gifts on them, they may by a free choice among themſelves chooſe ſuch for to be Paſtors, Teachers, Elders and Deacons, as they judge meet; who are to be fed by the free gift of the Flock they feed, while they watch for their Souls, and by the Vineyard they dreſs, while they ſee the garden of his Church be weeded, that no Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or Thorns grow there; but all live in the unity of the Spirit, and bond of Peace, ſtanding faſt in the Liberty, that Chriſt hath made them free, and be no more entangled with the Yoke of Bondage.</p>
            <p>Now, to help forwards this glorious Work in this day of ſo great Deliverance already begun, that God would be pleas'd to put into the hearts of the Supream Power in this Nation to make the People Free, Freeing them from the Yoke of Spiritual Bondage, that we may ſee in this our day, that word fulfill'd, that <hi>Kings ſhall be Nurſing Fathers,</hi> as was King <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> King <hi>Ezekiah,</hi> and that young King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> and in ſo doing will bring their Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Honour to Chriſt in his Church, which is Chriſts Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Body; <hi>who hath the Sun for her Cloathing, the Moon for her Footſtool, and the Twelve Stars for a Crown upon her;</hi> She having by Faith and Holineſs put on Chriſt the Son of Righteouſneſs that is riſen unto her, as ſhe hath learnt him of his Apoſtles, ſo is ſhe hereby advanced to heavenly Dignity, her Converſation being in Heaven, She loveth no more this world, of which her ſelf is not, but Travelleth with pains of Child-Birth, that Chriſt may be form'd in his Elect, calling them out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> this falſe Eccleſiaſtical State of Egyptian Darkneſs, <hi>into his Marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Light, to ſhew forth the Praiſes of the Lord in Sion, where the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35942:8"/>Lord God is a Sun and Shield, the Lord will give Grace and Glory, and no good thing will he withold from them that walk <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, Oh that all would lay to heart theſe things, and examine themſelves, whether they are in the Broad Way that leadeth to Deſtruction, or the Strait and Narrow Way, that leadeth to Everlaſting Life; ſeeing how many ſorts of People do plead that they are worſhipers of the living God, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering (as every one ought) by whoſe appointment and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they do worſhip God; for the Turks boaſt, how that they worſhip the Living God, and concerning Chriſt (as one ſaith) the Turks are well contented, that Chriſt be a Holy Prophet and a moſt Worthy Creature, yea, the Word of God, the Soul of God, and the Spirit of God conceiv'd of the Holy Ghoſt, and Born of <hi>Mary</hi> the Virgin, but will in no caſe grant him to be the Son of God, therefore no Law-Giver to them in Worſhip; ſo that they worſhip God, by the directions or appointment of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> according to his wicked <hi>Alcaron;</hi> therefore both they and their Service or Worſhip is not accepted of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Papal Religion boaſt, That they are Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipers of the Living God, and do in word, Profeſs <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be the Son of God; yet they by no means will acknowledge in Works, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the Son of God, Law-giver to them in Worſhip, but do Worſhip God, by the Counſel and Direction of ſundry Popes and Prelates, as Lord-Biſhops; ſo that for this reaſon among others, neither themſelves, nor their Worſhip can be accepted of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And will not Proteſtants conſider then, that as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, there is but one Law-giver in Worſhip, that is, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Prophet, Prieſt and King in his Church, who was Faithful as a Son over his own Houſe; if he be ſo, why then is the Service Book, the whole form of Worſhip in Proteſtant Churches, which Chriſt hath not given for directions in Worſhip in his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, but is taken out of the Popes Maſs-Book, as when it was tranſlated into Engliſh, the Men in <hi>Devonſhire</hi> Rebelled, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing their Service was altered, to whom King <hi>Edward</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, If the Service in the Church was good in Latin, it remained good in Engliſh; for nothing is alter'd, but to ſpeak with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that which was ſpoken in Ignorance; and to this agreeth the words of the Papiſts in their Supplication to King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, <hi>Anno.</hi> 1604. Reaſons of Religion.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:35942:9"/>
            <p>They inſult againſt Proteſtants, faying. That from their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure-houſe, the Religion now Eſtabliſhed hath learn'd the form of Chriſtening, Marrying, Churching of Women. Viſiting the Sick, Burying, and ſundry other like, as the Bocks Tranſlated out of theirs, do declare.</p>
            <p>Theſe being ſo groſs, that the Lord Jeſus ſhould be ſo deſpiſed, who is the Wiſdom of God, that Proteſtants ſhould deſpiſe-the Holy Order of Worſhip in Chriſts Teſtament, and ſo deny him to be the Son of God, Law-giver in Worſhip, which the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians walked in for the firſt three hundred years, un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill about the middle of the fourth Century, until <hi>Paſtors</hi> or <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſought after Dignities to be Church Princes as aforeſaid, they about that time begun to take upon them the office of Chriſt, to be Law-Makers in Worſhip; Oh therefore that the Lord would open the Eyes of all Proteſtants to conſider theſe things before it be too late, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt off from them the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Service-Book, together with that Prelatical Prieſt-hood, whoſe Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſucceſſively they have receiv'd from the Pope, as well as that Jewiſh and Ceremonial Heav Offering of the Law of Tythes, remembring what the Lord ſaid to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they came out of old <hi>Egypt,</hi> left Written for our Admonition, that are come out of the Spiritual <hi>Egypt, After the doings of the Land of</hi> Egypt <hi>wherein ye dwelt, ſhall ye not do, neither walk in their Ordinances; my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall ye do, my Ordinances ſhall ye keep to walk in them, I am the Lord your God. Wherefore if ye be dead with Christ from the rudiments of the World, are ye Subject to Ordinances, touch not, tast not, handle not, which all are to periſh with the uſing</hi> after the Commandment and Doctrine of Men, and as a warning to all, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>In vain do ſuch Worſhip God, whoſe fear towards God is taught by the Precept of Men;</hi> ſo then the ſure Rule is given by Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed are they that do his Commandments, that they may have right to the Tree of Life, and enter in through the Gates into the City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing then all mens Traditions in Worſhip it Idolatry, and no Idolator <hi>ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> &amp;c. as there is Men Idols, as well as Idols made of other matter: For when <hi>Iſrael</hi> had made to themſelves a new Miniſtry in Worſhip to God, not mentioned in the Law of <hi>Moſes:</hi> Theſe were called by the Word of the Lord, <hi>Hol-Shepherds,</hi> Zach. 11.17. even ſo, whatſoever People ſhall make to themſelves now in days of the Goſpel, if another Miniſtry than Chriſt hath appointed in his Teſtament, in the Breach of the ſecond Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they are <hi>Idol Shepherds;</hi> ſo that hence it is, ſaith <hi>John, Many Deceivers are entred into the World, and the World heareth them;</hi> ſo that after many Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations to the Churches of God, one was, <hi>Little Children, keep your ſelves from Idols,</hi> Amen, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.2.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
